Register of the Ignace Jan Paderewski papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ignace Jan Paderewski papers
1687-1983
75017
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 album box, 2 envelopes, 1 motion picture film reel, memorabilia (5.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, clippings, printed matter, and photographs relating primarily to the establishment of an independent Polish state, the Paris Peace Conference, Polish politics in the interwar period, the occupation of Poland during World War II, and the musical career of I. J. Paderewski. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941.
Modjeska, Helena.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copy of the motion picture film in this collection is available for immediate access; digital copy also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Ignace Jan Paderewski (also known as Ignacy Jan Paderewski) was a Polish statesman and musician.
1860 November 6 Born, Kurylowka, Podolia, Ukraine
1872 Studied music, Warsaw Conservatory
1876 Taught piano, Warsaw Conservatory
1880 Married Antonina Korsak, who died a year later
1882 Studied in Berlin under Friedrich Kiel
1884-1887 Studied in Vienna under Theodor Leschetizky Taught at Strasbourg Conservatory
1887-1891 Made first public appearances as a pianist in Vienna, Paris, London, and New York
1893 Composed "The Polish Fantasia" for piano and orchestra (Opus 19)
1896 Established the Paderewski Fund in support of musical compositions in the United States
1898 Settled in Riond-Bosson near Morges, Switzerland
1899 Married Helena Gorska
1901 Composed the opera Manru
1909 Director, Warsaw Conservatory
1910 Presented the City of Krakow with a monument commemorating the victory of the Poles over the Teutonic Order upon the 500th anniversary of the Battle of Grunwald
1915 Member and representative to the United States, General Committee for Polish Relief (organized in Switzerland in January)
1917 Member and representative to the United States, Polish National Committee; frequently urged Woodrow Wilson to include Poland in his Fourteen Points
1919 Prime Minister and Foreign Minister of Poland; delegate, Paris Peace Conference Resigned November 27 and returned to Riond-Bosson
1920 Delegate plenipotentiary of Poland to the League of Nations
1921 Resumed musical career in Europe and the United States
1938 Author (with Mary Lawton), The Paderewski Memoirs
1939 President, Polish National Council (Rada Narodowa) of the Polish Government-in-Exile, Paris
1940 Left Europe for the United States
1941 June 29 Died, New York City
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, speeches and writings, clippings, printed matter, and photographs relating primarily to the establishment of an independent Polish state, the Paris Peace Conference, Polish politics in the interwar period, the occupation of Poland during World War II, and the musical career of I. J. Paderewski.
Polish people--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Poland--History--1918-1945.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Statesmen--Poland.; Motion pictures.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1889-1983 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Affidavit, certificates, correspondence, eulogies, financial papers, lists, will, and clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Affidavit re attack of Jewish organizations and defamatory fliers, 1941, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Announcement for the inauguration of a bronze statue by Milo Martin to the memory of Paderewski, Morges, Switzerland, 1948 July 3 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Financial papers
    Affidavits, bank statements, bills, correspondence, income assessments, income tax returns.
    - General (Box-folder 1: 3-6)
    - Estates
      - Paso Robles (Box-folder 1: 7)
      - Santa Maria (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Sao Paulo (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - List of decorations (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Includes notes, table arrangements.
  - Subject file
    - Audience with Pope Pius XI. Notice and clipping, 1925 January 15 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Birthday, 80th. Acknowledgments for birthday greetings, and tribute by Gustave Doret (in French) (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Concert tours
      - Correspondence, 1923-1936
        Includes letters relating to other musicians or music in general, including Ernest Schelling.
        - Incoming, including Alfred Cortot, William S. Hawk, Vladimir Horowitz (Box-folder 1: 14)
        - Outgoing [See also: CORRESPONDENCE/Engles, Musaceous, Musikurs, Schelling, Steinway, Urchs] (Box-folder 1: 15)
      - Programs and income figures, 1924-1927? (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Death
      - Certificate (Box-folder 1: 17)
      - Condolences, notices, and resolutions, 1941-1983 (Box-folder 1: 18)
      - Eulogies
        - Polish Government-in-Exile (London) (Box-folder 1: 19)
        - Strakacz, Sylwin. Biography prepared for the Polish press (Box-folder 1: 20)
        - Syski, A., Arlington National Cemetery (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - Delegation assignments
      - Paris Peace Conference, 1919. Letter of resignation as delegate to the Paris Peace Conference, addressed to Jozef Pilsudski, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 22)
      - League of Nations, 1920. Telegrams of acceptance and of resignation, addressed to Prince Sapieha, late 1919?, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - Family
      Mainly correspondence with or about.
      - Gorski, Waclaw (son of Helena Paderewska by first marriage), 1922-1928? (Box-folder 1: 24)
      - Kodrebski (distant relative), 1926 (Box-folder 1: 25)
      - Paderewska, Helena (Mrs. I. J. Paderewski), 1925-1926 (Box-folder 1: 26)
      - Paderewska, Maria (sister). Paderewski's telegram on her behalf to Maxim Litvinov, 1936 (Box-folder 1: 27)
      - Paderewski, Alfred (son), 1891 (Box-folder 1: 28)
      - Paderewski, Jan (father). Document signed by Jan Paderewski (in Russian), 1889 (Box-folder 1: 29)
      - Paderewski, Jozef (half-brother), 1924-1939 (Box-folder 1: 30)
      - Wilkonska, Antonina (sister), 1941 (Box-folder 1: 31)
        Includes legal documents.
    - Honorary degrees [See: CORRESPONDENCE, Columbia University and Harvard University]
    - Memberships. Correspondence
      - Bohemian Club, San Francisco, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 32)
      - Institut de France, Paris, 1926 (Box-folder 1: 33)
    - Name Day. Congratulatory message signed by Polish soldiers interned in Switzerland, 1941 February 1 (Box-folder 1: 34)
    - Travel
      - Departure from Switzerland and travel through France and Spain en route to the United States (September). Correspondence and clippings, including re arrival in the United States (November 6), 1940 (Box-folder 1: 35-36)
      - Miscellany (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Will and testament, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 38)
    Holograph and photostat positive copy of entire document and related papers.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1894-1941 (Boxes 2-5)
  Letters, notes, and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Includes some correspondence of Helena Paderewska, and some in the hand of Paderewski's secretary, Sylwin Strakacz.
  - General
    - Drafts of letters and telegrams addressed to different people on the same sheet, 1921-1941 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      Correspondents include Bishop Adamski, King Albert of Belgium, Mrs. Szymon Askenazy, Albert Blondel, Adolphe Boschot, Raoul Choussaud, Jan Ciechanowski, Marja Cielewiczowa, Count Clauzel, P. Czescik, Jozef Dowboz Musnicki, Mrs. Drohinska, Hamilton Fish, Waclaw Gorski, Princess Gortschakoff, Adam Grzymala-Siedlecki, Henri Guisan, Joseph Haller, August Hlond, J. Horodyski, Count Jancoyski, S. W. Jarakomski, Tadeusz Jentys, Reverend Kasaczun, Jan Koch, Mrs. Krajewska, Stanislaw Kruczek, Mary Lawton, Maxime Leroy, Irene Loevenberg, Mr. Martinet, Stanislaw Milaszewski, J. Modzelewski, Andrzej Moszczynski, Jozef K. Orlowski, Jozefowa Pilsudska, Andre Poniatowski, Wladyslaw Raczkiewicz, Jan Romaszkiewicz, Theodore and Mrs. Roosevelt, Wladyslaw Sikorski, Colonel Smigielski, Jan F. Smulski, Mr. Sobinski, Wladyslaw Sobanski, Marquise de St. Paul, Stefan Starzynski, Maurice Sternberger, Mrs. Venizelos, Mr. Wielowieyski, Woodrow and Mrs. Wilson, and August Zaleski.
    - Miscellany (incoming) (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Unidentified (Box-folder 2: 3-4)
      Includes a letter to a Norwegian journalist, 1924?
  - Aballi, Sanchez, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Adamowski, Antoinette and Joseph, 1923-1929 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Adamowski, Gertrude and Tim, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Adatci, Count, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Addor, Barbey, 1934 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Aikins, James A. M., Sir, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Albert I, King of the Belgians, and Queen Elisabeth, 1929-1940 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    Includes letter from Court Marshall regarding the Queen's intercession with Berlin to facilitate Prince Ladislas Radziwill's departure from German-occupied Poland.
  - Alexandry, Baron d', undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Amster, Marc, 1935 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Astor, John Jacob, undated (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Association of Polish Students, University of Madison, Wisconsin, 1929 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Bank Zwiazku Spolek Zarobkowych, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Bannister, L. Ward (Mile High Club, Denver), 1923-1926 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Barthelemy, A. (Union League Club, Chicago), undated (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Beck, James M., 1925 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Beck, Louise C., 1924 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Behmeyer, L. E., 1924 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Benes, Edvard, 1935 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Benham, W. B. (University Club, Dunedin), 1927 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Berthelot, Philippe, 1921-1928 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Besson, Bishop, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Blazejowski, Boleslaw, 1935 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Bliss, Anna B., 1924-1926 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Blodgett, Eleanor, 1921-1929 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Blondel, Albert, 1924-1934 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Bojnowski, L., 1941 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Bok, Edward W., undated (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Borchard, Mr., 1928 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Borglum, Gutson, 1929 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Bourn, Agnes and William, 1923-1926 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Bratianu, Elise and Jean, 1924-1927 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Burbank, Luther, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Burnham, Hubert, undated (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Burton, Theodore E., 1928 (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Call, Mr., 1928 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Cambridge University (Dr. Seward, Dr. Stewart), 1926 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Car, Mr., 1921 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Cartier, Baron de, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Carton de Wiart, Adrien, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - Cazalet, Victor A., 1925 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - Chabrie, Robert (Journal des Debats), 1929 (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - Chlapowski, De, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - Chlusewicz, Colonel, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 47)
  - Ciechanowski, Jan, 1923-1941 (Box-folder 2: 48)
  - Cieplak, Archbishop, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 49)
  - Clauzel, Count, 1926-1934 (Box-folder 2: 50)
  - Clay, P. T. (Sherman and Clay), 1923-1926 (Box-folder 2: 51)
  - Coffey, Herbert V., undated (Box-folder 2: 52)
  - Columbia University (Murray Butler, Frank D. Fackenthal, Levering Tyson), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2: 53)
  - Comite International pour le Placement des Intellectuels Emigres, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 54)
  - Condon, Robert E., undated (Box-folder 2: 55)
  - Congres General de l'Enfant, Polish Committee (Witold Chodzko, M. Gromski), 1925 (Box-folder 2: 56)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 57)
  - Corboult, Miss, 1934 (Box-folder 2: 58)
  - Cumming, Joseph M., undated (Box-folder 2: 59)
  - Czartoryski, Witold, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 60)
  - Daily Mail, undated (Box-folder 2: 61)
  - Daladier, Edouard, undated (Box-folder 2: 62)
  - Damrosch, Walter, 1923-1935 (Box-folder 2: 63)
  - Daniels, John (English Speaking Union), 1928 (Box-folder 2: 64)
  - Daniels, Josephus, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 65)
  - Davis, Norman H., 1926? (Box-folder 2: 66)
  - Deering, Frank and Mrs., 1924-1926 (Box-folder 2: 67)
  - Deschamps, Eugenie, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 2: 68)
  - Dobrzycki, Rector, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 69)
  - Doret, Gustave, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 2: 70)
  - Downes, Olin and Marion A. (Boston Sunday Post), 1923-1932 (Box-folder 2: 71)
  - Drobinski, I., Mrs., 1923 (Box-folder 2: 72)
  - Drummond, Eric, 1929 (Box-folder 2: 73)
  - Dubowski, Ignacy, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 74)
  - Duer, Sophie Lawrence, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 75)
  - Dunham, Josephine and Theodore, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 2: 76)
  - Dworzak, J., 1922 (Box-folder 2: 77)
  - Dydejczyk, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 78)
  - Dziennik, Edmund A., 1928 (Box-folder 2: 79)
  - Eames, Henry Purmort, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Echo de Paris, L', 1933 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Eden, Anthony, 1936 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Emerson, Mary Hopkins, 1936 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Encyclopedia, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    Includes letter to unidentified minister regarding Wydzial Narodowy Polski w Ameryce.
  - Engles, George, 1923-1929 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Farnell, Mrs., undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Ferrell, Garland (Wichita Daily Eagle), 1923 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Fisher, Harold H., 1927 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Fisher, Herbert (Oxford University), 1928 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Flagler, Anne Lamont, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Foch, Ferdinand, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - France Pologne, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Fronczak, F. E., 1924 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Fuchs, Helene, 1922 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Fulcher, Maurice, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Gabrilovitch, Mr., 1926 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    Relates to Theodor Leschetizky.
  - Gandhi, Mohandas, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 18)
    Includes a transcript of a statement by Gandhi on Poland.
  - Garbarek, Feliks, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Garfield, H. A., 1926 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Gasiorowski, W. (Kolegium Zwiazku Narodowego Polskiego), 1926 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Gaspari, Cardinal, 1922 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Gibson, Hugh and Ines, undated (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Gilchrist, H. L., 1933 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Giraudoux, Jean, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Glasgow, Lord Provost of, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Golde, Edith Sullivan, undated (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Goral, B. X., 1922 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - Gorzynski, Monsignor, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Graham, Ronald, Sir, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Grappin, Henri, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - Gregory, D. J., 1925 (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - Gronkowski, Reverend, undated (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - Grudzinski, Ludwik, 1925-1928 (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - Gryncewicz, Joseph, undated (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - Haig, Douglas, Sir, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - Haiman, Mieczyslaw (Polish Roman Catholic Union of America), 1940 (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Halecki, O., 1940 (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - Haller, Joseph, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - Hamilton, Ian, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 40)
  - Hanotaux, Gabriel, 1929-1940 (Box-folder 3: 41)
  - Hartwell, Dr. and Mrs., undated (Box-folder 3: 42)
  - Harvard University (Thomas W. Lamont, A. Lawrence Lowell), 1926 (Box-folder 3: 43)
  - Hauke-Nowak, undated (Box-folder 3: 44)
  - Hedinger, 1924-1929 (Box-folder 3: 45)
  - Hempel, General and Mrs., 1929 (Box-folder 3: 46)
  - Hemphill, William, 1924 (Box-folder 3: 47)
  - Hlond, August, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 48)
  - Holiday, W. R., undated (Box-folder 3: 49)
  - Hood, C. H. (Minneapolis Club), undated (Box-folder 3: 50)
  - Horodyski, J., 1925-1941 (Box-folder 3: 51)
  - House, Edward M., 1923-1931 (Box-folder 3: 52)
  - Houston, Herbert, undated (Box-folder 3: 53)
  - Hovart, Izabella, 1928 (Box-folder 3: 54)
  - Howard, Esme, Sir, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 55)
  - Hrehorowiczowa, undated (Box-folder 3: 56)
  - Hymans, Paul, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 57)
  - Iwanowski, S., 1924 (Box-folder 3: 58)
  - Jeffries, Joseph M. N., 1926 (Box-folder 3: 59)
  - Jentys, Tadeusz, 1924-1934 (Box-folder 3: 60)
  - Jezierski, Norbert, 1927 (Box-folder 3: 61)
  - Jusserand, Jean Jules, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 3: 62)
  - Kaczynski, Monsignor, 1929-1941 (Box-folder 3: 63)
  - Kamienski, B. S., 1921-1923 (Box-folder 3: 64)
  - Karszo-Siedlewski, Tadeusz, 1936 (Box-folder 3: 65)
  - Kazimierczak, Andrzej, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 66)
  - King, Bradley, 1921 (Box-folder 3: 67)
  - Klarkowska, Anna, undated (Box-folder 3: 68)
  - Klobukowski, A., 1919 (Box-folder 3: 69)
  - Kolszewscy, 1921 (Box-folder 3: 70)
  - Korfanty, Wojciech, 1924-1937 (Box-folder 3: 71)
  - Koscisz, Jozef, 1936 (Box-folder 3: 72)
  - Koskowski, Boleslaw, 1929 (Box-folder 3: 73)
  - Kossak, undated (Box-folder 3: 74)
  - Kotarbinski, Jozef and Lucyna, 1924 (Box-folder 3: 75)
  - Kraczkowski, Jan P., undated (Box-folder 3: 76)
  - Kubicki, Franciszek, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 77)
  - Kulisz, K., 1928 (Box-folder 3: 78)
  - Kwapiszewski, Michal, 1920-1941 (Box-folder 3: 79)
  - Lambert, Alexander, 1929 (Box-folder 3: 80)
  - Landau, Rom, 1934 (Box-folder 3: 81)
  - Lansing, Robert, 1921 (Box-folder 3: 82)
  - Lar, George, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 83)
  - Lasocki, Zygmunt, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 84)
  - Laudon, Sir, undated (Box-folder 3: 85)
  - Laurence, Sister, 1922 (Box-folder 3: 86)
  - Lazare-Levy, 1935 (Box-folder 3: 87)
  - Lempke, Herman, 1921 (Box-folder 3: 88)
  - Le Pan, A., 1922 (Box-folder 3: 89)
  - Leroy, Maxime, 1935 (Box-folder 3: 90)
    Relates to Francis Plante.
  - Letellier, Henri (Le Journal), 1925 (Box-folder 3: 91)
  - Lewandowski, E. P., 1936 (Box-folder 3: 92)
  - Leygues, Georges, 1929-1933 (Box-folder 3: 93)
  - Lhevinne, Joseph, 1922 (Box-folder 3: 94)
  - Liga Morska i Kolonjalna, 1935 (Box-folder 3: 95)
  - Lloyd George, David, 1920-1935 (Box-folder 3: 96)
  - Lopot, Professor, 1936 (Box-folder 3: 97)
  - Loucheur, Louis, 1929 (Box-folder 3: 98)
  - Lubomirski, Prince, 1920 (Box-folder 3: 99)
  - MacAdoo, W. G., 1923-1926 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - McCormick, Chauncey, 1924 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Mangeot, Mr. (Monde Musical), 1923-1930 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Marlborough, Duchess of, 1928 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Mason, Madeleine Manheim, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Messmer, Sebastian, 1921? (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Meyer, Eugene, Mrs., undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Mickiewicz, Marie, 1921 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Mikolajczyk, Stanislaw, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Milaszewska, Wanda, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Mizerski, Stanislaw (Towarzystwo Uczestnikow Powstania Wielkopolskiego), circa 1925 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Modzelewski, J., 1927 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Morgenthau, Henry, 1921-1932 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Morning Post (London), 1926 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Moscicki, Ignacy, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Moton, R. R. (Tuskegee Institute), 1923 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Motta, Giuseppe, undated (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Muhlstein, undated (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Mullaney, B. J., 1928 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Muret, Henri, 1925 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Musaceous, 1923-1926 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Musikurchs, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Mussolini, Benito, 1925-1939 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Nansen, Mr. and Mrs., 1921 (Box-folder 4: 24)
    Includes list of Polish refugees in India.
  - Napieralska, Emily (Polish Day Committee), 1925-1934 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Nelson, Congressman, 1928 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - New York Times, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - New York Tribune, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - Niewiadomski, Stanislaw, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - Northcliffe, Lady, undated (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - Nossig, Alfred and Mrs., 1925-1936 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - Noulens, J., 1919-1939 (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - Noussane, Henri de, 1925 (Box-folder 4: 33)
  - Nowicki, Consul, 1920 (Box-folder 4: 34)
  - O'Donnell, James, 1929 (Box-folder 4: 35)
  - Olchowicz, Konrad, 1929-1935 (Box-folder 4: 36)
  - Opienski, Henryk, 1921-1924 (Box-folder 4: 37)
  - Oraczewski, Monsignor, 1923 (Box-folder 4: 38)
    Includes letters to Mr. and Mrs. von Moschzisker and others relating to Oraczewski.
  - Orlowski, Jozef K., 1921-1935 (Box-folder 4: 39)
  - Owens, Mayor, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 40)
  - Perlowski, 1926? (Box-folder 4: 41)
  - Pernod, Maurice and Mrs., 1925 (Box-folder 4: 42)
  - Petain, Henri Philippe, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 4: 43)
  - Phillips, Charles Joseph, 1921-1923 (Box-folder 4: 44)
  - Piekarski, Felix A., circa 1925 (Box-folder 4: 45)
  - Pierne, Gabriel, 1923 (Box-folder 4: 46)
  - Pilet-Golaz, Marcel, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 47)
  - Pizzardo, Monsignor, 1929 (Box-folder 4: 48)
  - Plante, Francis, 1924-1929 (Box-folder 4: 49)
  - Polignac, Marquis de, 1924 (Box-folder 4: 50)
  - Polish American Congress (B. Celichowski), 1925-1926 (Box-folder 4: 51)
  - Polish Army Veterans Association (Dziob; S. Z. Stachowicz), undated (Box-folder 4: 52)
  - Polish Falcons of America (F. J. Klosowicz, Teofil A. Starzynski), 1926-1941 (Box-folder 4: 53)
  - Polk, Frank L., 1923 (Box-folder 4: 54)
  - Poniatowski, Andre, 1933 (Box-folder 4: 55)
  - Ponzone, Count, undated (Box-folder 4: 56)
  - Popiel, Adam, undated (Box-folder 4: 57)
  - Posner, Stanislas, 1929 (Box-folder 4: 58)
  - Pourtales, Guy de, 1929-1934 (Box-folder 4: 59)
  - Przezdziecki, Henryk, 1931-1935 (Box-folder 4: 60)
  - Rabska, Wladyslawowa, 1925 (Box-folder 4: 61)
  - Raczkiewicz, Wladyslaw, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 62)
  - Raczynski, Edward, 1925 (Box-folder 4: 63)
  - Ratajski, Cyryl, 1924-1934 (Box-folder 4: 64)
  - Rawlings, Bernard, 1925 (Box-folder 4: 65)
  - Renie, Henriette, 1936 (Box-folder 4: 66)
  - Reymond, Arnold, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 67)
  - Reyntiens, Alice, undated (Box-folder 4: 68)
  - Rhode, Paul P., 1922-1929 (Box-folder 4: 69)
  - Robinson, Mrs., 1921? (Box-folder 4: 70)
  - Rond, General le, 1925 (Box-folder 4: 71)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1939-1940 (Box-folder 4: 72)
    Includes letter relating to the Polish Red Cross in Vichy France.
  - Rosenthal, Manzycy, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 73)
  - Rosset, Miss, 1934 (Box-folder 4: 74)
  - Rothermere, Lord, 1932 (Box-folder 4: 75)
  - Draft of letter to Rubinstein, Arthur, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 76)
  - Ruiz, Eduardo, 1921 (Box-folder 4: 77)
  - Rybnik (Poland). City Council, 1936 (Box-folder 4: 78)
  - Rzeczpospolita, 1924 (Box-folder 4: 79)
    Correspondence regarding the financing of the newspaper. Includes a letter from Wydzial Narodowy Polski w Ameryce.
  - Sands, Robert Cornell (Strollers University Club), 1925 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Sarolea, Charles, 1933 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Satterlee, Herbert and Mrs., 1921 or 1922 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Sauerwein (Le Matin?), undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Sawicki, Joseph F., 1923-1926 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Schaad, Herman, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Schaw, Henry H., 1922 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Schelling, Ernest and Lucy, 1921-1940 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    Includes letter of Peggy Schelling.
  - Schrembs, Joseph, 1923 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Sears, Sarah, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    Includes a telegram also addressed to Mrs. Bradley.
  - Seyda, Marjan, 1920 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Seymour, Professor, undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
    Relates to Colonel House's papers.
  - Sforza, Carlo, 1933 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Sikorski, Wladyslaw, 1926-1941 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1941 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    Includes a reprint of an address by Sinclair, "To The Conquered Peoples of Europe."
  - Siwinski, G. W., 1925 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Skirmunt, K., 1925-1939 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Skolimowski, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Skrzynski, Aleksander, undated (Box-folder 5: 19)